okay
okay good so
um
can you guys see the full screen
yes yeah okay good good all right uh
well
good to see you all there in Egypt it
sounds like a great workshop and um
uh you've got some big buddies of mine
uh Fernando and Pedro there I think it's
somewhere in the background I don't know
um
so you've got a interesting great week
ahead with lots of exciting speakers
um and I think it's kind of uh an honor
for me to be able to present
um probably what I would say is one of
the most
interesting and important
um attempts at some sort of a general
theory of what's going on in the brain
from an algorithmic perspective
um
the Bayesian brain predictive processing
active inference and the free energy
principle
uh so
um you know I can see you guys all there
um I wonder if if by a show of hands I
could like anyone could put up the hand
if they feel like uh they they
um have a have a grip on the free energy
principle and active inference anyone
put up their hand
how about something easier like anyone
like familiar with the kind of basic
Bayesian brain hypothesis
okay so you know a few so okay we'll
we'll okay we'll look we're gonna go at
it slowly
um and I assume that like most people
have a kind of a mathematical background
so so that's gonna make it a little
easier
so we'll start from
um philosophy and you know the basic uh
the basic place we start is
from the nature of perception so you
know I'm outside I'm looking at a tree
and
um
I kind of just see a tree and it's just
amazing but
we are thinking well somehow
um I form some sort of a representation
of that tree in my mind and um and of
course
what we what we begin to understand is
that actually if I've always perceiving
just the representation of the tree in
my mind then I'm not really perceiving
the tree as it is in itself you know
that's a sort of philosophical issue
um and also the other thing that I must
be doing is I'm also forming a
representation of myself and that is so
uh in our in our minds ah you know we're
also forming some sort of representation
of ourselves and it's a big issue in
philosophy how this works and
you know one of the first great
philosophers to really uh start to nail
this is Emmanuel Kant
um uh in the um
the 18th century and what he
showed is that look
um we only experience the phenomenal
world the things as they appear to us
and we have to when we use the
categories of space and time and
causality to arrange our perceptual
framework and these kind of things like
space-time causality are kind of hyper
prized that we bring to bear to organize
our sensory appearance our sensory data
and what he called it is that he thought
that he had created some sort of
copernican revolution
in uh in the in the mind Sciences in the
sense that he said look it's objects
that must conform to our cognition
rather than cognition
conforming to objects
and this was a huge insight and
um you know about a hundred years later
helmholtz a very famous physicist system
psychologist
um started to crystallize this as
perception as inference
and this is really where
um where where the where the free energy
principle and
um predictive processing starts with
when we look out from our eyes
unlike what uh sort of Descartes the
typical view that Descartes might have
helped we are not just passively
um experiencing what's coming through
our eyes
um perception is kind of hard
um
if you look at this video what you see
is roughly speaking what we might see in
accurately if you could actually see
what's coming through your eyes because
all that we can perceive through our
eyes is a very very small Central area
of the of the Immaculate for where
um and it's very difficult to see what's
going on and by the way you know most of
it's in black and white only the central
partisan color so if we actually
see what I was what you're actually
seeing now you can see much clearer that
you know you're perceiving this B
um
um buzzing around a flower now it's very
difficult to make sense of the the dot
on the left but somehow our brain
constructs
a whole image now how is that done
um that is done that is called the
Bayesian perception problem and the
basic problem is this we receive
some sort of that you know that we're
assuming that there is something out
there in the world
which are the causes of our perception
actually according to Kant we can't
really say much about this at all but
what we do get is sensory data so U is
some sort of
um large Vector of uh sensory data and
the problem for the agent is that we
have to form something called the
recognition density which is the
probability probability distribution of
like what are the causes of my sensory
data given
my
sensory data what are the causes of my
Sensations given my sensory data now
that of course is
um solved by using
um basis theorem
um and basis theorem as you as you know
this this term here what we're trying to
solve for is the posterior the
probability of the sensory of the um
causes of my Sensations given my sensory
data and to solve that we have to use
two terms as well as a normalizing term
underneath here
um we start with our prior probability
of what do we before receiving any data
what do we expect
um the what is our background prior
beliefs around the uh causes of this of
these features in the world that there
are trees in the world for example in
their agents and then the second term is
the likelihood of the data what is the
probability of getting this particular
sensory data
given
that it comes from my best guess which
is a tree so in other words How likely
am I to to receive these particular
Sensations given that there's a tree out
there my hypothesis of what's going on
and underneath is the probability of
receiving this sensory data in the first
place which is a kind of normalizing
term
now that normalizing term
actually is is very difficult to compute
it's an infinite integral you basically
have to go through every single
hypothesis of you know this sensory data
could be caused by a tree could be
caused by a mountain it could be caused
by
um you know some sort of hallucination
you know you couldn't possibly do it
it's computation explosive
so although Bayes theorem is the
mathematically optimal solution that
maximizes the value of all information
it is absolutely the correct
mathematical solution
we cannot solve it we cannot solve it
using machine learning because it's
computationally explosive and evolution
cannot solve it our biological beings
cannot Solve IT explicitly so how do we
get around it well we can draw
inspiration
from machine learning techniques like
artificial neural networks
um so artificial neural networks
um you know train on on whole loads of
of sensory data so whole loads of data
for example this particular neuron could
train on a whole load of faces
and as it learns as we adjust these
synaptic weights it starts to do
something called feature extraction
so
at low levels of the sensory data at the
low levels of the neural network it
extracts low level features like Edge
oops sorry edges and corners and little
things like this no level features at
Mid levels of the network it's
extracting mid-level features like noses
and eyes and ears and then at high level
um areas it extracts the high level
features like
um whole faces for example
but the question is you know how do
these networks train these networks
um uh train essentially by being
provided some ground truth sensory data
so what we do is go through something
called supervised learning okay so the
way supervised Learning Works is that we
really know what a true face is you're
given all these thousands of examples of
true faces and then what happens is that
we we get a new face of sensory data and
um we we take a guess this network has
not yet trained it takes a guess at what
this is this could be a cat or a or a
dog or a face and
what we know is is whatever this um
whatever this image is it could be as I
said um you know anything a cat or or a
dog or a face
um we actually know the true category
um it could it's actually a face and so
we can compare the guess of the neural
network with the ground truth the true
features and that sets up a prediction
error and we use that prediction error
signal or generally we Square it uh uh
because then the derivative is very
simple and we we basically you know
apply multivariate calculus to minimize
the prediction error and adjust all
these synaptic weights so that the error
is is minimized and and step by step the
the neural the neurons start learning
that's a very famous algorithm called
the back propagation algorithm
now the problem with that is that there
is no supervisor in the brain who is
giving us the ground truth data who is
saying this is a cat this is a dog this
is a face
there isn't anyone even if you're told
as a child you know this is a cat two or
three times that's simply not enough
data to kind of do uh supervised
learning
so somehow the brain must be doing this
in an unsupervised way
so how might we be doing that well
there's only one thing we know okay we
don't know the ground truth the only one
thing we know
is the data itself
and so if we have to guess if we only
know the data itself and we're trying to
guess a feature Vector in other words
what are the features of my experience
dogs cats faces
um edges you know I mean
whatever features there are
what we can do is a brilliant strategy
which is to try to uh take a get try to
learn this net feature Network and then
whatever we guess at we then say let me
then assume that that's the feature in
the of the world those are the causes of
my sensory data and let me generate
a network going the other way to
construct some predicted
some predicted data let me simulate what
I would be seeing if there was a cat and
a dog and a face in this picture
and that is
um and and then we can compare the
predicted
data that I the the predict what what
I'm what I'm guessing are the
predictions and the actual sensory data
and that's that's a prediction error
and that is used to train the network
now this kind of network is called
um in general an autoencoder and uh
there are three parts of the network the
first part is the recognition model or
the feed forward model
um
uh which is which is trying to go from
the data to a feature Vector the the
code this gray bar here is called the
code if any of you have heard of
predictive coding well the code that
they're referring to in predictive
coding is basically this line here
this series of neurons in the middle
here and then the second part is the
generative model this is generating what
I would be seeing
um if this was the correct uh
features of the world
and that second part of the model is
called a decoder as well so
the problem is that this kind of network
is extremely difficult to train
um because it's very non-linear it's
very you know there are too many
possibilities and and data is ambiguous
and difficult to decipher
so
um these kind of networks especially the
type of network that called the
variational autoencoders are trained
using
um something called free energy as an
objective function rather than just the
prediction error and free energy takes
into account the prediction error that
we talked about
Plus
it takes into account
prize prior probability around what you
would expect this feature Vector to be
all right
um and
that gives us a a principled way to
train the network
okay
so this kind of network that we just
showed in with Gene learning we can take
inspiration from that
inspiration and last week I was with uh
all week with a whole lot of scientists
including
um uh Carl friston who's who's really
one of the the founders of the free
energy principle in fact the the kind of
key architect and he actually warned us
about
um kind of trying to use machine
learning
um analogies however
he felt that this particular analogy is
a very good one and so I commended to
you to really think about how the brain
is working so we we're using this model
as a kind of idea of how the brain is
working except that
in the brain
what happens is that this top Network
can you this this green Network this
generative model actually folds back
onto the feed forward Network so I don't
know if this animation is coming through
clearly but that was supposed to
illustrate the network
folding back onto itself
and the feed forward Network the blue
Network
kind of goes up and in fact what
actually travels up according to the the
predictive processing framework is not
the data itself but simply the
prediction errors simply these
prediction errors travel up and what's
actually happening is that this
generative model is taking a guess from
the latent layer the code and the
feature vector and generating what I
would be seeing and and the only thing
that's traveling up is the prediction
error as compared to this charitable
model so this is the fundamental idea of
what is going on in predictor pressing
except that
this is probably happening in a
hierarchical way we have a number of
these kind of models that are going on
organized in sort of layers and
and then what happens is that these
criers are actually arising from higher
level models in the brain
um and and prediction errors actually go
up to these higher level models and
prize for this higher level model are
coming from even higher level models in
the brain and so they could be maybe you
know who knows how many layers in this
you know perhaps half a dozen layers in
this kind of hierarchical predictive
processing framework
okay
so let's look at specifically how the
variational
algorithm is supposed to work now
as we said we we see you know there are
certain features in the world that uh
we're assuming are generating our
sensory data this sensory data these
features in the world are generating our
sensory data
and we cannot solve bayes's theorem
correctly so what we have to do is we
have to form an inference we have to
make a guess
at an approach approximate posterior so
we make a functional form often you know
in these kind of models they're often
you assume to be gaussian for example
you know
um
multi-dimensional gaussian
um with certain parameters so this
probability distribution have certain
parameters Phi and that is instantiated
in the example that I gave it's
operationalized in the feed forward
Network that we talked about the
recognition model the blue Network at
the bottom of the auto encoder
and from this
approximate posterior we then have an
estimate of the code this this red bar
here
which is the features an estimate of the
features in the world that there's a
tree that there's an agent
and from there we then create we have a
generative model which in the brain of
course feeds back
um on itself
and the output of the generative model
is a is a the sensory data that I would
be my expectations of what I would be
seeing in the world in this case I don't
know if you can see this this sort of
little tree that sits on top of the
generator model
and from there we then are in a position
to compare the predicted data U Dash and
the actual data
and we get a prediction error and that
is at the heart of trying to train this
model but as I said before
there's one more factor that goes into
the free energy and that is
the deviation
from my prior expectations how different
are these features from my prior
expectation so for example
um if it if just using the prediction
you know if I thought this was a alien
spacecraft
um that had landed that would have a lot
kind of a low prior probability and so
uh that would mean that these causes are
kind of far away from my prior and um
that would mean that I would be
penalized for thinking it's a alien
spacecraft
and using this free energy which
combines both the prediction error and
this kale Divergence which is
essentially the distance or some sort of
inverted commas distance it's not
actually a metric
um from my prior expectations I can then
train this this recognition model and
the generator model itself to minimize
free energy and I will hopefully
slowly slowly
get a convergence between this
approximate posterior and the real
posterior you know a really accurate
image of what's going on
and that in a nutshell is the
variational algorithm to solve
approximate Bayesian inference
now
uh before we move on
um again uh show of hands I just I I
know you're sort of a mathematical crew
but how many people are familiar with a
relative entropy KL Divergence can
someone can you have a show of hands
please
okay I can see maybe two three okay fine
so this is a this is really important
and and um
since I understand you're supposed to be
like understanding the stuff at a
technical basis so let me let me let me
just go through this because this is
kind of important it's very easy I'm not
gonna
um but
but this this basic idea is that the KL
Divergence between two probability
distributions
is essentially measuring something like
a distance that you know how far away
are these distributions how different
are these distributions and the
particular form that that this
functional form has is is
um
you basically compute
you take uh this the first probability
distribution uh P log of p over Q okay
and so these are the two distributions
you're trying to compare but what it
really means the take-home message that
I want you to say is what it really
means is how much information how much
information
suppose that I thought
that um a Treasurer was buried
on a straight line let's say a road
going between zero and one okay and I
have no information otherwise my my kind
of probability distribution is um Q of X
I don't know where the treasurer is
buried it could be anywhere along this
line
and
it's me a kind of a more accurate map
saying actually the treasures buried
between
um
0.87825 0.825 and one right here P of X
this is a new information that I get a
more accurate probability is Fusion how
much information
have I got how many bits do I get from
going from Q of x to P of X what is the
informational distance and that uh
informational distance is roughly
speaking how many yes no questions
I have how many bits of information how
many yes no questions I have to go from
Q of x to P of X and you know it's kind
of easy I could say is it on the left of
Q of X or the right of Q of X that's
question one so it's on the right okay
if it's on the right is it on the first
half or the second half it's on the
second half okay that's the second
question is it then I say is it on the
first half of the second half of that
and it's in the second half so it's p of
X so three questions so in fact if I
compute this this uh sum and let's just
do it like an integral because it's the
same thing
um
what I see is
um that I can actually compute that it's
pretty easy integrals like this this is
eight and then that's log of 8 p of X is
is a height of eight because the area
under the curve is one and Q of X is one
and times one you know the error on the
curve and if I compute that I get
exactly three bits because this this
this integral limits give gives me 1 8.
okay so anyway just wanted to explain
that
um that it's a very simple calculation
it's roughly speaking the informational
distance I I worry about using the word
distance and Metric if you want a real
metric you have to use something called
the Fischer information distance and you
integrate this KL Divergence and then
you get you know you get into the kind
of wonderful informational geometry that
I'm sure Fernando is going to be talking
to you about
so
um
right
as I said this is not a metric because
it's not symmetric but let's not worry
about that now let's get into the real
heart of it because you're here to learn
about the free energy principle and I'm
only going through this not to kind of
uh do a shock in all but actually to say
in fact how simple this is you will see
as you go through your you know as you
go through uh your careers in this whole
area that
people are Bamboozled by all the
mathematics around the free energy
principle and actually it's relatively
easy to to do but
um it's couched in very technical uh
uh tensor calculus okay and it's kind of
difficult to unravel so I hope you will
later on come back and say oh well that
was a beautiful explanation that you saw
here in Egypt
so the basic idea is is
um to solve the fundamental problem that
we talked about what are the causes of
my sensory data
and
and we're going to use basis theorem but
as we just saw we cannot use basic serum
directly because it's computation
explosive so we're going to use a
variational algorithm we're going to
approximate the actual posterior that
we're trying to learn with we're going
to approximate it with this Q of this Q
distribution which is you know for
example could be a simple form like a
gaussian with some parameters
um
multi-guard
um uh
distribution
and
um we are going to uh try to minimize
the distance inverted commas
um technically the KL Divergence between
q and P
so
we're going to minimize the Callback
Library Divergence between the Q
distribution and the true posterior P by
changing the parameters of the
underlying distribute distribution okay
so what does that mean
um
uh does this come across this this
equation can everyone see it yeah yeah
okay good so this says
please minimize
um by changing these parameters of the Q
distribution the KL Divergence between p
and Q all right how do we do that well
um I showed you the functional form of
what a KL Divergence looks like this is
just the definition of it all right that
sounds straightforward enough and we
just sum over all the categories V all
the particular features it could be in
this
now you'll immediately recognize that
when I sum with the probability in front
that's basically an expectation value
right so I can basically rewrite that as
the expectation of this log of Q over P
distribution
um so here's the expectation under the Q
measure this is a measure of probability
measure under the Q probability measure
it's it's this distance now of course
I've just put a minus sign instead of
dividing because that's just a property
of logs okay you can separate out the
logs in this way very simple
and then we're just going to use bases
theorem because what we recognize is
look this is the probability of of the
features given my data and that is here
on the side that is just the posterior
well if I take logs of this posterior
here
then I get a log in front on this side
and of course when I multiply
um things the logs add and when I divide
the the logs uh you subtract so
essentially this here which is the
positive the law the the log of the
posterior simply becomes this which in
these these are just the terms the
likelihood of the data that's the term
as this term here this is the prior the
log of the prior and this is the log of
the probability of the data the
normalizing term
okay so this is just applying basis
theorem
and then we just rewrite this in very
simple terms we simply take the prior
and put it in
with the first term and then we separate
out the other two terms okay
and what we then have a simple rewriting
is we recognize that
the first term here
is nothing but another KL Divergence of
this form except that
what we have is a KL Divergence between
the approximate posterior
this this this this
um this Q distribution and the prior
probability of V okay and
then these terms here are simply the
expected value under the Q uh measure of
the um
log probability of the sensory data of
the likelihood of the data and then this
term here this term here I can take out
of the by the way I could take out of
the expectation operator because it
doesn't depend on uh Q at all right so
there's you know there's nothing
stochastic here so I can just take it
out and then finally so we can notice
that it's a constant
now these first two terms are the free
energy
okay
um this first term here
um the KL Divergence and then the second
term the um the expected uh surprise I'm
gonna come on to see why that's called
surprise so this term here is roughly
speaking how surprising is the sensory
data what is the expected surprise
of the scent of this data given that I'm
assuming that given this feature given
that I think it's a tree how surprising
is this sensory data so if you if you
look it's a negative log if you remember
logs go from minus infinity to zero so
if we put a negative sign it goes from
plus infinity all the way down to to
zero and um if you have um if the if
it's very very surprising if it's not
very surprising at all in other words
this is precisely the kind of sensory
data that I would expect given that it's
a tree it's not very surprising
um it's got a it's got a low it's got a
high probability of being this kind of
sensory data given that it's a tree then
it's not very surprising if on on the
other hand it's like really unsurprising
you know I'm seeing
something that is more like um uh snakes
and crocodiles then
um it's very surprising data and so this
term would be highly surprising so the
first term in the in this term in the
free energy is surprise how surprising
is my sensory data in other words how
good a fit is this explanation for the
data the second term
on this the first leading term here is
the
KL Divergence between the
um between the uh the the posterior that
I've that I've learned and the prior so
take a look at this furry animal here
it could be
actually let's suppose that it's equally
likely to be a dog a cute little furry
dog with blonde hair or a polar bear
okay in other words let's suppose that
the surprise of the sensory data given
that it's a polar bear is equal to the
surprise that it's that it's a dog in
other words they in other words the data
fits both the dog model and the polar
bear model
but
polar bears especially walking around in
Egypt
um
are very unlikely the prior probability
of seeing a polar bear in Egypt is very
low
and so this term would be a very high
distance between the posterior that it's
a polar bear and uh and the prior that's
better so you'd be very much penalized
remember we're trying to minimize free
energy here
okay so these are the two terms of of
free energy now I'm sure you're probably
asking and no one ever explains in in in
Neuroscience why is this called free
energy I mean I I thought the free
energy was something to do with entropy
and energy and like stuff like that you
know Jewels you know this is information
this is not Jules well it's called the
free energy because you can rewrite this
term I won't explain how this is very
easy to rewrite this from from this line
here into a slightly different format
and you can check it for yourself that
it's possible to do this and this
happens to be this way of rewriting this
free energy term here happens to be
equal to
exact I mean isomorphic
with
the helmholtz free energy in
thermodynamics okay and the reason for
that is because this term here
is the average energy
um you remember you when you sum up and
multiply by probability uh this this
thing here which which is going to turn
out to be the energy of the explanation
that's the average energy and this is
the entropy minus log P log uh uh uh uh
P log P sum is the entropy okay so
here's the end so energy minus entropy
or average energy minus entropy if as
you might recognize is the typical form
of a free energy and and then you might
say well why on Earth is this an energy
this is an energy if you you know for
those you remember you know have done
physics the boltzmann distribution in
thermodynamics is that the probability
is related to the energy by an
exponential term so if I take log of
both sides I get rid of this exponential
term so then the minus sign comes over
and hay pressure minus log p and that is
equal to the energy so that's called the
energy of the explanation the energy of
the explanation that this is a tree
so that is the free energy so there you
have it and now you can forget all about
it because you've seen it once in your
life once you've seen it in your life
it's been demystified and you can say uh
it wasn't magic after all
so
now
um I I need to move on a little bit
faster so I'm actually just going to to
whiz through some of these uh bits but
but roughly seeing that
um what this is basically saying is that
is that
um there's a very nice approximation and
and of this free energy principle and
the takeaway message is that the
posterior belief the posterior that
you're forming is roughly speaking the
weighted average of your priors and your
sensory evidence your priors and the
sensory evidence coming from the
likelihood and the
the weights
of that weighted average turn out to be
the precisions of the distribution in
other words how if your Precision is
inverse variance in other words if your
prior is particularly sharply focused
you know low standard deviation
then it's going to be highly weighted
within the posterior or if you get very
accurate data okay you're gonna
um highly weight it within your
posterior okay
um right so
now
so we've got this basic hierarchical
model and these precisions that we
talked about how sharply influenced are
going to influence the in the top-down
ratings top down weighting of the priors
compared to the sensory data now
in the brain we've got a kind of
cortical hierarchy and that
is
the the hierarchy that I'm talking about
in the in the um hierarchical predictive
processing framework is precisely going
to be that
um uh it's it's a homologue of the
hierarchy in in the cortex and this is a
very nice machine learning
um exercise that was done to try to
figure out the cortical hierarchy and
you know very similar similar things to
to what one might imagine you know low
level sensory percept so low level
features mid-level features like motion
and rotation and faces and then at the
right at the top of the cortical
hierarchy are language and Concepts and
reasoning
as you might expect and of course this
hierarchy is probably best not
represented as a as a pyramid structure
but in fact from a hierarchical from a
predictive pressing point of view it's
really seen as these these different
channels of
um streams of hierarchical predictive
pricing models until they start
integrating together perhaps in some
sort of a global workspace or something
that you might learn about of course no
one has put together predictive
processing and Global workspace Theory
as yet people have tried to attempt it
to do that but I'm just kind of warming
you up and making you salivate to say
that um you know maybe these things
could fit together in some way you know
you have these uh predictive pressing
models of vision audition the motor
system actually goes outwards olfaction
somatosensory interception
gas station
the whole visceral proprioception
um and they kind of come together now
actually we're probably not going to
have time to go through the phenomenal
self model but it's super interesting
that in fact the self itself is nothing
but an internal model yeah within a
predictive pressing hierarchy uh
hierarchical framework
um and
so the basic upshot is that our
conscious experience
to the extent that we're conscious of
the generative model will be the
contents of our general model that is
the take-home message at what will
become a uh kind of predictive
processing Theory Of Consciousness as
yet it hasn't been worked out but if if
it is worked out
um the new the computational neural
phenomenology
assumption is that the contents of our
generative model is the contents of our
of our conscious experience to the
extent that we're we're conscious of it
so this is not completely worked out
because we've got to figure out what are
we conscious of but in other words you
know if I'm looking out of the tree I'm
going to have like a represent you know
a you know in my generative model this
this construction of a tree and a and an
avatar you know the self Avatar and some
thoughts and these thoughts could be
visual thought course and and auditory
thoughts blah blah blah and visceral
Sensations and proprioception
um and smells and sensations of the
breath at my nose and my the sense of my
heartbeat and sounds and emotions I can
like you know I'm constructing my
emotions in in a sense like uh as as
Lisa film and Barrett is kind of
described in this way and all these
contents of the generative model aren't
just sitting on top of each other until
unless you're uh kind of doing
psychedelics or in a meditative state
they're organized into a phenomenal self
model so what does that look like well
they are reorganized
I don't know if that
that animation came through okay I'll do
it again they are organized into
a subject object Duality so everything
in this blue area here is within a
subject uh there are internal
interception these are extra reception
um there's a certain perspectivity
there's a subject object relationship
there's a notion of agency there's
multi-sensory integration
um there's a sense of minus a kind of a
sense of a Cartesian theater these are
all constructions and that we're not
really aware of the fact that there is
this phenomenal self model and that's
called phenomenal transparency according
to the philosopher Thomas metzinger
so just to before I finish just to to
finish to finish up because the the real
fruit of this whole free energy
principle and pretty depressing
framework is something absolutely
um amazing which is that we can put
action into the same framework to
minimize free energy and that is called
active inference and to be honest I
think that that's a real that's though
that's why this framework is so amazing
because it kind of unifies action and
perception in a single framework
and Carl friston came up with with this
kind of idea in the in the um maybe
around 2008 and nine
um and and the way it works is that
essentially you the way you could put it
is that the goal States let's say I'm
trying to reach over to grab an apple
um uh you know and the apple is here in
green if you can see and I'm currently
here well
if the way it sets up is it puts that
getting the apple is in my prior I have
a prior expectation to get the Apple
that's kind of my reward goal states are
embedded into the price and then
immediately there's a prediction error
between where my finger is at the moment
my hand is at the moment and where I
want it to be getting the apple right
and so this prediction error will be
resolved not by changing my perception
but by moving my muscles
in other words doing action
um and so inference and action are
resolved together and there is a
movement trajectory until the prediction
error is minimized and I got the Apple
absolutely astounding so the way okay I
won't go through this but this is this
is what you're gonna finally understand
later on and I just don't want you to be
mesmerized by this but this is um the
kind of Final Act of inference framework
with action in it and it's typically
instantiated in a partially observed
Markov decision-making process under
active inference so the way this works
is that what we saw before is that I'm
trying to predict my
um my sensory data these o is the
outcomes the outcomes of my kind of you
know the the World shows me my sensory
data these this is this is the sensory
data and I'm trying to model
the world and that's these states these
are internal models of the world and
these matrices uh which which a
probability transition matrices don't
worry about the details about these you
know how these are formed
what I need to do when I bring action in
is that I need to have some sort of
preferences some sort of goal stage
which are called preferred
um preferred observations this is this
Pro this is a probability distribution
over my preferred outcomes and that is
gives me my my expected free energy and
uh the expected free energy and then I
have my prize around my habits uh you
know your habitual actions and the
Precision waiting over this expected
free energy and that gives me my
policies of the world and the whole
thing is minimizing expected free energy
so
that is a uh that's a quick Whirlwind
Tour on um on this framework and we can
go to questions now
okay
I can hear us yes we can right okay good
when you see me as well yeah
Okay cool so who's good questions okay
let me saw you first there you go
[Music]
um
uh
um the
um machine learning analogy that you
side reflect it like seems to uh
suggests that your signal
kind of enter and learning happening in
the brain
or like
um like some like other aspects of the
energy
maybe yours can you hold it because can
you hear me well it goes rather as if
you're talking underwater
um
is this
okay yeah yeah uh start over the
um
machine learning analogy your side
reflects seem to suggest that your
singer for Android learning will be
happening in the brain
where like
um like a from like other aspects of
like free energy principle that I have
read about it's um organization
uh I was wondering very few
could comment on if that can be
brought together in some sense
or if that's like
or that does the contradictory views
okay yeah look I think
I think you have
um
I think you have uh put your finger on a
very important uh issue which is that
you know I don't think we have the granu
well first of all take the machine
learning phenology as simply pedagogical
right uh uh this is really to introduce
and try to make sense of the pre-energy
principle
um how is being instantiating in the
brain is something we we really don't
have
um good models and and data over yet uh
so I think it's a great question and I
think you should think about working on
that
[Laughter]
other questions
uh I think that is first
um I think you can ask the question okay
hi Shamil all right good to see you here
I didn't I didn't know you're out there
so great
can you hear me yeah
okay great
um so uh
Predator processing is not in itself a
theory of Consciousness uh but clearly
it has implications for Consciousness I
noticed that you framed most of the
discussion in terms of perception rather
than Consciousness and it seems like
free energy principle in general
comments a lot more explicitly on that
rather than Consciousness
um does Carl or anybody else
um who is working on the free energy
principle
um explicitly distinguished between
perception and Consciousness what is the
difference right can they be treated as
the same okay so as I mentioned the
whole of last week I was at a workshop
with Carl friston Anil Seth Jacob Howie
um Thomas metzing you know the you know
the whole leaders of this whole area
um on
computational neural phenomenology and
that what you're asking was precisely
what we were debating back and forth
here you know and it was very it was uh
very interesting so
I would say that
so you know we are right at the
beginning of of saying look
we have our conscious experience
and we know that the
and we have the neural going on and we
know that the brain must be solving some
sort of Bayesian influence problem so
it's a good way of approximating
what's going on in the
brain is by modeling it as kind of a
predictive pressing framework and given
that we are trying to given that
um
a phenomenal experience is
you know if you take a functionalist
perspective a phenomenal experience is
somehow being worked out in terms of
neural goings-on
um you can then say that the predictive
processing model is going to be a
homologue of what is going on in the
brain but also what is going on in
phenomenology so we're precisely trying
to draw you're absolutely right to to to
to to to ask this question but we are
explicitly say trying to draw an analogy
to say yes indeed this is a way
the the project of of
um
computational neural phenomenology is
precisely
using
um active inference Frameworks for
example or other computational models to
model our phenomenal experience and and
if you want to drill down further if
you're assuming some sort of active
inference framework then I would even
say that
that um
parts of the posterior or the posterior
is
the homologue of what is our conscious
experience and our Precision weightings
are the homologue of our attention
mechanism in other words the sort of you
know if I if I really pay attention to
this
um this bottle of water then in my
posterior remember the Precision waiting
is the is is is is the weight that
that's used as the to calculate the
weighted average in my posterior so you
know this is strongly weighted into my
into my posterior distribution otherwise
my my Consciousness is deeply in
um uh
dominated by this bottle okay
so great question you're right at The
Cutting Edge we don't have a theory of
Consciousness which is based around
predictive pressing however what I'm
trying to say to you is that it's
starting to look very evocative
thank you so much
any other questions yep
so actually my question is exactly
pretty similar to Ken's question so
actually I I've read from a lot of
places like oh people always supporting
processing active reference is not
really a theory of Consciousness it's
just a framework but at the same time I
got so confused so for example I see a
lot of adversary anniversarial
collaboration is now trying to test the
prediction of predated processing or
active inference between these
predictivity theories and other theories
so it's a framework or it's a theory if
it's just a framework then it does not
really review for example necessary
review for example in the background
masking why sometimes I see the stimuli
and why the other times I do not
um
yeah and and and if this if it is a
theory then it is a theory then it's
normal framework then it should give an
explanation to
so for example why backward masking
binocular rivalry works so guys you know
guys and girls what you're seeing here
is how science is actually you know the
the sausage making
there is a you know there are people
Anil Seth and Jacob Howie have written a
paper to say predictive processing is
not a theory of consciousness
and then other people like uh Adam
saffron a couple are just a year you
know go kind of created something like a
really interesting Theory Of
Consciousness called integrated World
model Theory which is essentially
integrating aspects of Predator
processing Theory and combining it with
the global workspace theory in the kind
of sense that I alluded to about sharing
of information at the center of the ring
and actually also combining it with
areas of the back of the brain in IIT
terms right and so actually integrating
it in and basically what you're seeing
is
the kind of
maneuvering in the field where people
think ah we're kind of grappling towards
a predictive pressing Theory Of
Consciousness it's not yet clear it's
not like 20 years old like uh or 20 30
years old like Global workspace Theory
or iot or something you know it's we're
right at the beginnings of this I
predict
that we will have a you know a theory of
Consciousness based around predictive
processing
I also predict that people will say
that's not a theory just like people say
other theories in our Theory you know
and there'll be lots of argument and
there'll be you know and I think that
will be a richer process for thinking
about Consciousness because actually I'm
kind of partial to the view that
you know
recurrent processing theories IIT
theories Global workspace theories
higher order theories and predictive
processing theories are all bringing
something important to the table and
actually at a at assc which is the main
Consciousness conference last year
um there was a debate in that whole
thing between these four theories and
there was supposed to be a fifth Theory
except
that Anil Seth had long covered so he
couldn't come but you know there were
five theories that were put up for
debate so good question
but you know see the messy process of
Science in front of you
yeah yeah yeah I I'm just really
confused it's like for example even a
new says like at the Wayne Palm paper he
just say one thing oh is it pretty it's
just a framework but at the same time
you can also see his reviews in nature
reviews uh Neuroscience lately like a
serious Consciousness is still listed as
one other Theory and he is in
participate but if you know that is not
the theory why do you still participate
in anniversary collaboration testing it
as a theory of Consciousness I just you
know I just don't get it also like
it's it's it's it's it's wonderful
it's wonderful and nuanced and in that
Nuance we might get progress
unfortunately at The Cutting Edge
science is always confusing you know
literally everyone at the conference
lasts a week was confused and that was a
sign of progress
thank you
anymore
you know I think the teachers should
feel free to ask questions as well
uh yeah hi thank you for your talk
um I was just wondering because actually
the free energy principle also tries to
explain more than just the brain right
um so it's more or less a theory of
everything so how is your take on that
like what can predictive processing tell
us more than about the brain okay great
yeah that's a very good point and I
didn't bring that out but thank you for
asking a question on that
so
confrustin often says that there are two
ways into the free energy principle one
is the low road and one is the high road
and I took the low road which is through
um inference and then there's another
road which is called the high road which
is
based around
um
the concept of Markov blankets and
Markov blankets are essentially
think of them like
um like informational boundaries like
for example a cell membrane for a cell
that all information has to go through
the cell membrane and so if you look at
the informational states of the cell
membrane you will get that all the
information inside will that has come
from outside will have to have been
represented on the on the blanket states
on the bat on the mark of blanket States
now
it's it's essentially saying that if you
have a Markov blanket then
you are going to be instantiating a
model
of
the external data and this is very
powerful and this you know the the sort
of principled information theoretic
arguments that have been proofs that
have been trying to be given for this
and this means that
everywhere you see a Markov blanket not
just in the brain but in the body
perhaps in the organs perhaps in the
cells perhaps ecosystems perhaps
the planet Earth you know I mean
even species I mean you know even you
know within in the in the evolutionary
tree and species and things like that
you know you're going to see this kind
of what
um is called in the in the area Bayesian
mechanics
um and I think it's a wonderful idea
it's a very powerful
um idea you know and um it's very
evocative so yeah just that's a brief
Glimpse
um of of how that is and I've just
focused on the brain
yeah but there is uh is there a way to
detect a mark of blanket like when you
see something like okay this is a mark
of blanket and this is not one or is
that just like you could basically see
it everywhere depending on your
definition or yeah no that's that's a
very good question to be honest
I think most markup blankets are only
approximate and and that's an issue um
in theory but but
you basically have to see so the
canonical example would be some sort of
system
that is
Auto poetic and self-organizing and and
continuing through time so if a system
exists so this is how the I'm sketching
a little bit how the proof works if a
system exists the nature of existence is
that it's a system for itself which
means that there is a Markov blanket so
just to call it that there exists a
system instead of saying that we can
define a system self-contained kind of
system like this which means that the
fact that it's self-contained in this
way means that it's got a Markov blanket
so this is a great question because
um because
you know this stuff is very powerful I
mean there was a paper written a couple
of years ago which was saying a general
theory of everything every space thing
and like officer like the thing was
things that exist I mean it was really
deep stuff and anything that exists
exists with itself has a Markov blanket
because that's what it means that it
persists through time and one of the
just just just very quickly because it's
kind of a cool thing if it persists
through time as a system one of the
things that it must be doing is also in
practice
not being broken down by entropy
surviving against the SEC the threat of
the second law
uh uh unless it's thermodynamic entropy
and so
a system has a model of its external
environment you know and and acts in
such a way as to avoid the second law so
this is a sort of interesting argument
to say that things like homeostasis and
action are are ways of instantiating
active inference
um in order to
or as a result they it means the system
continues to exist which is resists the
second North thermodynamics
very interesting thank you
so now that we have applied free energy
to every space thing uh I think we can
finish here thank you very much Emil for
the amazing talk
and uh
yep
all right thank you so much thank you
and good luck for the rest of this
Workshop